Guide to the Morris and Dorothy Margolin film collection, 1947-1982 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Morris and Dorothy Margolin film collection 1947-1982 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Margolin, Morris, 1908-1990
10.0 linear feet Extent: 4839 Items
Born on July 28, 1908 in Brooklyn, New York, Morris Margolin spent most of his life in the New York metropolitan area, where he worked as an accounting teacher before starting his own accounting firm. In 1936, Morris married Dorothy Safran. The Margolins were avid travelers and Morris captured many of their overseas trips in motion picture films and slides, sharing them with friends and family as well as members of the Metropolitan Film Club and B'nai B'rith. The Morris and Dorothy Margolin film collection dates from 1947 to 1982 and includes twenty-five 16mm and seven Super 8 motion picture films created by Morris Margolin, chiefly documenting Morris and Dorothy's international travels. The films include footage from Pakistan, Bulgaria, Ethiopia, and Kenya -- rare destinations for Western travelers in the 1950s, 1960s, and 1970s. Highlights include an abundance of images of the Soviet Union and Israel, and images of Capetown documenting the apartheid years. All of the films are color, and a few include sound elements such as narration, music, or even sound effects. The collection also includes a handful of home movies that document family trips and events such as graduations and birthdays, and one film that appears to be a professionally produced documentary about the Soviet Union. The films are complemented by over 4,000 color slides of still images taken during their travels. The collection, arranged chronologically, also includes Digital Betacam preservation tapes, DVD masters and DVD use copies.
RL.00844
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. However, original audiovisual materials are CLOSED to patron use. Use copies are available in the collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Morris and Dorothy Margolin film collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006 and 2011.
Biographical Note
Born on July 28, 1908 in Brooklyn, New York, Morris Margolin spent most of his life in the New York metropolitan area. He graduated from New York University (NYU) in 1926 and taught accounting at Far Rockaway High School in Queens, New York from 1933 to 1940. Morris was the founding partner of Margolin, Winer & Evans, an accounting firm established in Jamaica, New York, in 1946 that later moved to Garden City, Long Island. He was also a charter member and former president of the Jamaica, Queens, chapter of B’nai B’rith, a global Jewish community service organization.
In 1936, Morris married Dorothy Safran. Dorothy was born to Polish parents in Budapest, Hungary, on July 28, 1911. Her family emmigrated to the United States in 1913 and settled in New York City. Dorothy graduated from NYU, where she studied Spanish language and culture and also did graduate work. Dorothy was a lover of the arts and an active member of Women Strike for Peace. The couple had two daughters: Elaine born in 1940, and Linda born in 1944.
Morris was an amateur filmmaker, photography enthusiast, and classical music aficionado. The Margolins were avid travelers, taking an extensive series of international trips. Morris documented their travels through his photography and filmmaking and then shared his films with fellow members of the Metropolitan Film Club in Manhattan and at B’nai B’rith functions. The couple also hosted screenings in their home for friends and family.
Morris retired in 1970, and the Margolins soon moved to Palm Beach, Florida, where Morris continued to share his films and photos with new friends. Morris passed away in 1990, Dorothy in 2007.
Collection Overview
The Morris and Dorothy Margolin Film Collection includes 32 films that capture the Margolins' travels between 1947 and 1976. Destinations represented in the collection include Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria, Canada, Denmark, England, Ethiopia, France, Germany, Greece, Hawaii, Hong Kong, Hungary, Israel, Italy, Japan, Jamaica, Kenya, Majorca, Monaco, Morocco, Norway, Pakistan, Portugal, Puerto Rico, Romania, Scotland, South Africa, the Soviet Union, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Tanzania, Thailand, Turkey, and Yugoslavia. The films are complemented by over 2,000 color slides of still images taken in most of these same countries (1959-1982). Of particular interest are the slides from travel in the former USSR and Israel. Also included is a handful of home movies that document family trips and events such as graduations and birthdays, and one film that appears to be a professionally produced documentary about the Soviet Union acquired by the Margolins during their travels.
Particularly notable is the adventurous nature of many of the countries visited, such as the Soviet Union, Pakistan, Bulgaria, Ethiopia, and Kenya -- rare destinations for Western travelers in the 1950s, 1960s, and 1970s. The films are also noteworthy because Morris regularly trained his camera on his surroundings, recording everyday life as well as architectural and geographical features of the countries he visited. His wife Dorothy also makes frequent appearances in the films.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
The collection is arranged chronologically and includes Super 8mm and 16mm reversal originals as well as Digital Betacam preservation tape masters and DVD masters. DVD use copies of each film are available to researchers. All of the films in the collection are color. Many are silent, but some include voiceover narration, music, and even sound effects.
Film titles were taken directly from original labels and typically give an overview of destinations visisted on a particular trip. For most films, a preliminary or detailed shot list is included in the finding aid. These provide more information on specific cities and sites visited. Reel numbers were assigned by archivists during processing; they generally reflect order of accession.
Topical Subject and Genre Headings
Margolin, Dorothy; Margolin, Morris; Margolin family; Metropolitan Film Club; International travel -- Pictorial works; Tourism -- Pictorial works; 16mm; Amateur films; Color film (film); Home movies and video; Reversal film; Slides (transparencies); Travelogues (Motion pictures); Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Geographical Subject Headings
Austria -- Description and travel; Belgium -- Description and travel; Bulgaria -- Description and travel; Canada -- Description and travel; Denmark -- Description and travel; England -- Description and travel; Ethiopia -- Description and travel; France -- Description and travel; Germany -- Description and travel; Greece -- Description and travel; Hawaii -- Description and travel; Hong Kong (China) -- Description and travel; Hungary -- Description and travel; Israel -- Description and travel; Italy -- Description and travel; Japan -- Description and travel; Jamaica -- Description and travel; Kenya -- Description and travel; Majorca (Spain) -- Description and travel; Monaco -- Description and travel; Morocco -- Description and travel; Norway -- Description and travel; Pakistan -- Description and travel; Portugal -- Description and travel; Puerto Rico -- Description and travel; Romania -- Description and travel; Scotland -- Description and travel; South Africa -- Description and travel; Spain -- Description and travel; Sweden -- Description and travel; Switzerland -- Description and travel; Tanzania -- Description and travel; Thailand -- Description and travel; Turkey -- Description and travel; United States -- Description and travel; Soviet Union -- Description and travel; Yugoslavia -- Description and travel
Contents of Collection
- Reel 29: Happy Days Camp Life, 1947
  Use Copies: DVD use copy available soon.
  - Reversal original, 16mm, si., co., reel 1 of 1, (400 ft.) (Box 4)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: est. 11:06) (Box TBD)
  - Preservation DVD master, (TRT: est. 11:06) (Box TBD)
- Reel 30: Elaine's Graduation P.S. 178 / Greenbrier / Washington / Linda's Birthday / Phillips Castle, Rip Van Winkle, Tarrytown, 1953
  - Reversal original, 16mm, si., co., reel 1 of 1, (350 ft.) (Box 4)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: est. 9:43) (Box TBD)
  - Preservation DVD master, (TRT: est. 9:43) (Box TBD)
- Reel 1: France, Belgium, Switzerland, Austria, Italy, 1953
  Includes narration and music.
  title card: "Characters? - And How - Dorothy Frances Sam"
  map of Europe with title "Vagabonds 1953"
  deck of ocean liner
  interiors of ship
  ship's crew working
  life preserver labeled: "Ile de France / Le Havre"
  man smoking cigar; interiors of ship
  views of the ocean
  deck of the ocean liner, Dorothy walks toward camera, poses, waves
  interior of the ship, Dorothy walks toward camera
  interior of the ship, Morris and Dorothy walk toward camera
  three men (friends of the Margolins?) on deck of the ship
  Dorothy and friend relax in lounge chairs on ship deck
  Dorothy looks out at the ocean, walks to group and socializes on ship deck
  Dorothy, friend and Morris walk down stairs to deck and toward the camera
  Morris and Dorothy walk around on ship deck, up a set of stairs
  Morris poses near railing, ocean behind him; smokes a cigarette
  Morris walks around on deck with a friend, talking
  Dorothy and others on lounge chairs
  Dorothy poses near railing, walks around on deck
  street scenes in Paris, includes shots of Dorothy walking around
  sign: "Grand Marnier / La Maison du Café"
  street scenes in Paris
  Dorothy and friends turn around and wave at camera
  building: Louvre; Dorothy and friends nearby
  Arc de Triomphe and environs
  man (Sam Rosenberg?) walks toward camera, wiping his face, camera in hand
  woman (Frances?) walks across the frame
  "former Russian countess" tour guide in horse-drawn carriage
  scooter travels down narrow Parisian? street
  Morris and Dorothy walk into the frame, cross street
  Dorothy on roadside in rural Switzerland
  Alps, Dorothy waves from below, fellow travelers nearby
  mountain peaks, Rhone Glacier
  scenic shots of the Alps, some with Dorothy
  Dorothy and others stand near "former Hotel Grand Majestic Mattenhoffer"
  street scenes of Interlaken, Switzerland
  group climbs into car
  snowcapped Jungfrau
  street scenes of Innsbruck, Austria
  Innsbruck railroad station
  bombed out building near Innsbruck railroad station, Dorothy nearby
  couple walks by wearing traditional Austrian clothing
  jeep, American GIs?
  more bombed out buildings
  Dorothy walks toward camera, Tirol/Tyrol? Hotel in background
  Dorothy and Frances? in horse-drawn carriage
  exteriors of Palace of Franz Joseph
  bombed out buildings, underexposed and dark
  scenery, and horse, as shot from horse-drawn carriage
  Dorothy at mountainside restaurant, aerial view of Innsbruck
  visit to Vatican, includes Vatican Museum, Cathedral of St. Peter and St. Peter's Square
  Mussolini's balcony
  Monument to King Victor Emmanuel and Tomb of the Unknown Soldier in Rome
  Dorothy outside castle in Bruges, Belgium
  Manneken Pis in Brussels, Belgium
  lacemaker tatting near store: Real Belgian Lace
  Manneken Pis
  city square in Belgium
  Dorothy asks police men for directions
  flowers market on the square
  life preserver
  return trip on Steamship Independence
  close up: New York
  Dorothy and others relaxing on the ship deck
  narration snippet: "Enjoy yourself, honey. Just a couple of more days to go. You can still be a lady. And then back to scrubbing floors, scrubbing ears, and sending the kids off to school. Won't be long now, honey. Your holiday is over."
  empty lounge chairs on deck
  shots of the coastline of the Azores, Dorothy on deck
  Dorothy walks to ship deck with binoculars, looks at Azores
  more scenic shots of the Azores
  Dorothy, friends and others lounge on ship deck
  kids splash around in deck pool
  aerial shot of deck pool
  woman in bikini and high heels plays with a dog
  ship arrives in New York, passes Statue of Liberty in distance
  Dorothy poses with New York City skyline in the background
  Morris ends narration with: "The bar is now open. You may continue drinking."
  - Reversal original, 16mm, so., co., reel 1 of 1, (700 ft.) (Box 1)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: est. 19:26) (Box TBD)
  - Preservation DVD master, (TRT: est. 19:26) (Box TBD)
- Reel 2: French Riviera, Israel, 1953
  Israeli flag flying on top of a tower
  plane parked on tarmac in "the new state of Israel"
  sign: "Nazareth Souvenir Shop"
  street scenes, architecture
  sign: "Synagogue"
  children playing in the streets
  people ride donkeys through town
  town watering hole
  children ham it up for the camera
  "typical Arab home"
  locals pass by on mules
  goats grazing in field
  Sea of Galilee / Lake Tiberias and surrounding landscape
  kibbutz
  village
  street scenes in Safed
  Israeli soldiers
  catacombs
  Israel soldiers running along road
  sign in Hebrew
  Mount Herzl
  grave of Theodor Herzl
  Jerusalem from a distance
  children approach driver's side of car, as captured from passenger seat
  landscapes
  sign: "Haifa-Tel Aviv Road"
  scenes of Israeli soldiers, including women
  Israeli children playing, doing hand stands
  man on donkey in middle of the road
  in-transit camps, settlements for European refugees
  fortress in upper Galilee
  countryside, Hula Swamp area
  Morris and friend? inside fortress
  travel along newly constructed highways, captured from inside the car
  sign: "Danger-Frontier Ahead-No Passage (multiple languages)"
  cattle walk along the road
  sign: "Upper Galilee Regional Council"
  scenes at a kibbutz
  ruins of Arab city
  scenes of the Negev desert and Bedouin settlements
  Morris on a camel ride
  more scenes of the Negev desert and Bedouin settlements
  Morris stands next to tri-directional sign
  Weizmann Institute of Science in Rehovot, Israel
  landscapes, including olive trees
  people along roadside, captured from inside the car
  Morris stands next to tri-directional sign, ruins of Arab village in the background
  entering Jerusalem by car
  exteriors of King David Hotel
  path to Mt. Zion
  sign: "B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation at the Hebrew University"
  grounds of Hebrew University
  airplane on tarmac
  roulette wheel, stacks of coins
  title card: "Why 50 Million Frenchies Can't Be Wrong"
  Carlton Hotel in Cannes, France
  beach scenes
  Morris poses with woman on the beach
  friends? of Morris interact with the same woman
  swimming pool overlooking the Mediterranean
  life preserver: Eden Roc / Cap of Antibes
  Dorothy sitting on Eden Roc
  person dives into Mediterranean
  Dorothy and Frances rinse off
  swimmer climbs up hanging ladder from water
  fireworks
  - Reversal original, 16mm, so., co., reel 1 of 1, (500 ft.) (Box 1)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: est. 13:53) (Box TBD)
  - Preservation DVD master, (TRT: est. 13:53) (Box TBD)
- Reel 31: Camp Life, 1954
  - Reversal original, 16mm, si., co., reel 1 of 1, (175 ft.) (Box 4)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: est. 4:51) (Box TBD)
  - Preservation DVD master, (TRT: est. 4:51) (Box TBD)
- Reel 3: Liberté, England, Scotland, 1955
  blending of people waving from a pier and the Liberté docked in the harbor
  Liberté: Ocean Liner from New York City to London. On June 29, 1955
  ocean liner Liberté seen from port
  crowds and Margolin family seeing them off at pier. people on deck of Liberté
  view of New York City skyline, Statue of Liberty, and other boats taken from ship
  fire safety drill
  deck tennis
  crew working on ship
  transfer from Liberté to smaller boat to go to Plymouth, England
  London
  Grovener House hotel
  street scenes
  men in kilts
  shops
  traffic
  double decker bus
  Piccadilly Circus
  theatre district
  10 Downing Street
  school children
  Westminster Abbey
  Houses of Parliament
  Big Ben (in scaffolding)
  River Thames
  Scotland Yard
  St. Paul's Cathedral
  bombed out rubble from World War II
  New Bond Street
  Tower of London
  Buckingham Palace
  changing of the guard
  Princess Anne looking out of Buckingham Palace window
  small town outside of London
  outdoor market
  Oxford
  colleges
  High Street
  students
  Broad Street
  bicycles
  Stratford-Upon-Avon
  Ann Hathaway Cottage
  Warwick Castle
  punting
  Edinburgh, Scotland
  Edinburgh Castle
  Princess Street
  Scottish dancing performance
  Loch Katrine
  Loch Loman
  unidentified Scottish town
  sign: "England & Norway"
  - Reversal original, 16mm, so., co., reel 1 of 1, (1275 ft.) (Box 1)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: est. 35:25) (Box TBD)
  - Preservation DVD master, (TRT: est. 35:25) (Box TBD)
- Reel 4: Norway, Sweden, Denmark, 1955
  Use Copies: DVD use copy available.
  title card: "Our Trip to Europe"
  sign? England & Norway
  ocean liner in harbor: LEDA
  close-up on ramp to boat: Bergen Line
  luggage loaded onto boat
  group stands on ship, some wave
  Dorothy waves from top of ramp
  sign: "1st Class"
  boat deck shot from dock
  ship flying the Norwegian flag
  Dorothy climbs steps onto deck
  cars loaded onto boat
  Dorothy on boat deck, looking through binoculars
  sign on building: "Bergen Line - Quickest Route - Shortest Sea Passage - England & Norway"
  ship sets sail, view of harbor, other boats, the boat's own deck and passengers, including Dorothy
  scenery as seen from the boat
  preparations for boat docking?
  lush scenery
  Rutevogn with license plate R-1295
  Dorothy and friends inside Rutevogn, enjoying a meal
  street scenes in Oslo?: buildings, cars, traffic, pedestrians
  Dorothy window-shops, Arnt M. Kristiansen silverware?
  Dorothy leaves store with small package,
  street cars, buses
  Dorothy window-shops
  street sign: "Tordenskiolds gate 2-3"
  woman crosses the street
  Dorothy stands outside of unidentified building, interacts with two Norwegian children
  city park with gardens, fountain, sculpture
  street scenes, buildings
  pedestrians in park
  group gathered in park for performance
  scenery, banks of the Alna River?
  people gathered along street
  swan? and duckling waddle across a pathway
  four chefs carry out a very large cake
  performance in the park, and spectators
  narrow street
  uniformed men walk down street toward camera
  tour group, including Dorothy, gathers and then walks down street
  Stockholm? skyline and scenery, including industrial elements along waterway
  promenade along the water
  interior of unidentified building
  building: Margaretaskolan Hotell Stockholm
  street scenes, including busker and street vendors
  man gets his shoes shined
  street scenes, including pedestrians and bicyclists
  car with bicycle on rack
  uniformed man stands at corner, salutes approaching uniformed man
  street scenes, underexposed and dark
  boat: Athena, Göteborg
  Swedish flag
  Dorothy waves from boat
  boat trip includes locals waving from the river bank, scenes from rural Sweden, and traveling through locks
  Dorothy sitting on the boat with friends, painting her nails
  girl folds napkins on the boat
  young men stack flotation devices?
  locals gather to watch drawbridge raised
  shirtless Morris steers the ship, pipe in mouth
  boat passes through another lock?
  sign: "Batturer Gota Kanal"
  boats docked, Wilhelm Tham boat approaches
  sign with information about Motala Express, boat tour?
  Stora Hotellet in Jönköping
  Motala Express prepared for departure
  passengers on deck of Motala Express
  group of boys watches from bridge
  street scenes, including bicyclists
  Motala Express
  bridge moved for Motala Express
  Motala Express sets sail, view of Captain, passengers
  pedestrians and cars cross bridge
  view of the Lake Vättern
  entrance to Tivoli
  Wivex
  Dorothy looks at fabric at a sidewalk sale
  Strøget, the pedestrian zone in Copenhagen
  Copenhagen City Hall
  sign: "Danmark / Brandforskiring Livsforsikring"
  sign: "The Royal Copenhagen Porcelain Factory"
  sign: "Den Kongelige Porcelainsfabrik / Royal Copenhagen Porce[lain]"
  sign: "Bing & Grondahl Porcelain"
  interior of store, Dorothy interacts with salesperson, looks at silver trays, goblets?, candelabras
  street scenes, with a focus on bicyclists
  Dorothy near canal, boat with sign in background: Motorfaerge til Christianshavn
  Dorothy walks up steps from canal to street level
  Dorothy on platform with luggage cart, sign: "Jönköpings Central Utgang"
  sign: "Jönköping C"; Lake Vättern in background
  motorboats cruise by in canal
  scenes of unidentified city as shot from tour boat
  Dorothy on the boat
  Dorothy disembarks
  Little Mermaid statue, Copenhagen
  Dorothy at a park with windmill behind her
  Dorothy walks to bench, sits; Norwegian flag and Frederiksborg Palace? in the background
  building: Hotel Kobenhavn
  Dorothy on bridge; crowd walks toward Frederiksborg Palace?
  Carlsberg Beer sign in distance
  crowd walks toward Frederiksborg Palace?
  exteriors of Frederiksborg Palace
  tour group, including Dorothy, outside of Frederiksborg Palace?
  Dorothy on bridge
  bus with sign: "Copenhagen Excursions"
  bird nest on roof
  exterior and environs of Frederiksborg Palace?
  Dorothy walks across large square toward tour group
  exteriors of unidentified building
  Dorothy in courtyard, walks toward Hamlet Grill
  Scandinavian Airlines plane on tarmac; pilot and flight attendant walk toward camera
  flight attendant walks across frame
  airport staff prepare plane for flight
  passengers, including Dorothy, board the aircraft
  flight attendant poses near steps to plane
  planes taxi on runway, pans to airport terminal
  Dorothy seated on the plane, pans to other passengers
  title card: illustrated, "The End"
  - Reversal original, 16mm, si., co., reel 1 of 1, (1100 ft.) (Box 1)
  - Preservation tape master, Digital Betacam, (TRT: 31:21) (Box TBD)
  - Preservation DVD master, (TRT: 31:21) (Box 1)
- Reel 5: France, Italy, 1955
  Eiffel Tower, as captured from a boat cruising the Seine
  views of Paris from the Seine: bridges, buildings, other boats
  Margolins and friends on boat
  miniature Statue of Liberty
  more shots of the Eiffel Tower
  Notre Dame from the Seine
  man with movie camera on the boat deck, filming
  visit to Versailles, including gardens, exteriors, and some interior shots
  sign: "Marie Antoinette"
  roadway with directional sign: "Paris"
  close-up on directional sign: "Paris"
  Arc de Triomphe, eternal flame and flowers
  Obelisque de Luxor in the Place de la Concorde
  street scenes, Place de la Concorde
  Dorothy walks toward camera at Versailles?
  Dorothy interacts with woman selling lace
  gates of Versailles?
  woman selling lace
  Dorothy gets into car
  Dorothy crosses street, stops and poses near uniformed man, pans to large building
  Dorothy poses on narrow street, outside of Cinema Photo store
  exteriors of Versailles and the grounds, including Dorothy and Morris
  countryside, pond with water lilies
  sidewalk cafe, Dorothy at table
  Brasserie du Musee
  bicyclist on narrow street
  Dorothy walks across empty square
  sign on awning: Café A Tout Va Bien Tabac, pans to street scenes
  exteriors of unidentified church